This is a story about capitalism.
هذه القصة عن الرأسمالية .
It's a system I love
إنه نظام أحبه
because of the successes and opportunities it's afforded me and millions of others.
بسبب النجاحات والفرص التي أتاحها لي ولملايين آخرين .
I started in my 20s trading commodities, cotton in particular, in the pits,
في العشرينات من عمري بدأت تجارة البضائع، القطنية بشكل خاص، في السوق المخصص
and if there was ever a free market free-for-all, this was it,
وإذا كانت هناك سوق حرة فعلا، للجميع، فتلك هي
where men wearing ties but acting like gladiators
حيث الرجال يلبسون ربطات العنق لكنهم يتصرفون كالمصارعين
fought literally and physically for a profit.
كانوا يتقاتلون فعلا من أجل الربح بكل الوسائل
Fortunately, I was good enough that by the time I was 30,
لكن لحسن الحظ، قبل بلوغي ال 30 من العمر
I was able to move into the upstairs world of money management,
استطعت دخول عالم إدارة المال
where I spent the next three decades as a global macro trader.
حيث قضيت العقود الثلاثة التالية كممارس للتجارة الكلية
And over that time, I've seen a lot of crazy things in the markets,
وخلال هذه الفترة شهدت اشياء جنونية في سوق العمل.
and I've traded a lot of crazy manias.
وقمت بعمليات تجارية بهوس.
And unfortunately,
لكن لسوء الحظ،
I'm sad to report that right now we might be in the grips
وآسفا أقول أننا تحت وطأة
of one of the most disastrous, certainly of my career,
أخطر هوس وأواجهه في مسيرتي
and one consistent takeaway is manias never end well.
والحكمة أن أي هوس لا ينتهي على خير
Now, over the past 50 years,
خلال الخمسين سنة الماضية
we as a society have come to view our companies and corporations
كمجتمع نظرنا إلى شركاتنا ومؤسساتنا
in a very narrow, almost monomaniacal fashion
من زاوية ضيقة وهوس أحادي
with regard to how we value them,
بالنسبة لقيمتها لنا
and we have put so much emphasis on profits,
وقمنا بالتركيز بشكل مبالغ فيه على الأرباح
on short-term quarterly earnings and share prices,
على الإيرادات الربعية وسعر السهم
at the exclusion of all else.
متناسين الأشياء الأخرى.
It's like we've ripped the humanity out of our companies.
وكأننا نزعنا الإنسانية من شركاتنا
Now, we don't do that -- conveniently reduce something
نحن لانقوم بذلك (حصر الأشياء
to a set of numbers that you can play with like Lego toys --
بأرقام كأنها لعبة ليغو)
we don't do that in our individual life.
نحن لا نفعل ذلك في حياتنا كأفراد
We don't treat somebody or value them
فنحن لا نتعامل مع شخص أو نقيمه
based on their monthly income or their credit score,
بحسب الدخل الشهري وقدرته على السداد.
but we have this double standard
ولكن لدينا ازدواجية المعايير هذه
when it comes to the way that we value our businesses,
عندما نقوم بتقييم أعمالنا
and you know what?
وتعلمون ماذا؟
It's threatening the very underpinnings of our society.
إن ذلك يهدد دعائم مجتمعنا.
And here's how you'll see.
وهنا سترون
This chart is corporate profit margins going back 40 years
هذا مخطط لهامش ربح شركة على مدى أربعين سنة
as a percentage of revenues,
للنسبة المئوية للإيرادات
and you can see that we're at a 40-year high of 12.5 percent.
وترون هنا نسبة نمو 12.5% وهي الأعلى خلال 40 سنة
Now, hooray if you're a shareholder,
والآن إذا كنت مساهما ستسعد بذلك
but if you're the other side of that, and you're the average American worker,
ولكنك اذا كنت موظفا أمريكيا عاديا
then you can see it's not such a good thing.
يمكنك أن تلاحظ أن هذا ليس جيدا بالنسبة لك
["U.S. Share of Income Going to Labor vs. CEO-to-Worker Compensation Ratio"]
[حصة العمال من الدخل مع نسبة رواتب المدراء التنفيذيين إلى رواتب العمال]
Now, higher profit margins do not increase societal wealth.
إذاً هامش الربح المرتفع لا يساهم في زيادة الثروة المجتمعية.
What they actually do is they exacerbate income inequality,
بل يزيد من تفاقم عدم المساواة في الدخل.
and that's not a good thing.
وهذا ليس إيجابياً
But intuitively, that makes sense, right?
ولكن هذا بديهي، أليس كذلك؟
Because if the top 10 percent of American families
فإذا كانت العشرة بالمئة الأغنى من العائلات الأمريكية
own 90 percent of the stocks,
تمتلك 90 بالمئة من الأسهم
as they take a greater share of corporate profits,
فهم يمتلكون الحصة الأكبر من الأرباح
then there's less wealth left for the rest of society.
فهذا يعني أنه لن يتبقى الكثير للآخرين في المجتمع.
Again, income inequality is not a good thing.
مرة أخرى، عدم التساوي في الدخل ليس أمراً إيجابياً.
This next chart, made by The Equality Trust,
في المخطط التالي، من قبل منظمة ( ذي ايكواليتي ترست)
shows 21 countries from Austria to Japan to New Zealand.
يظهر21 بلداً من النمسا إلي اليابان إلى نيوزيلاند.
On the horizontal axis is income inequality.
في المحور الأفقي لدينا عدم التساوي الدخل
The further to the right you go, the greater the income inequality.
وكلما ذهبت إلى جهة اليمين ازداد عدم التساوي.
On the vertical axis are nine social and health metrics.
على المحور العمودي يوجد تسعة قياسات اجتماعية وصحية.
The more you go up that, the worse the problems are,
كلما ذهبت للأعلى ستزداد المشكلة
and those metrics include life expectancy, teenage pregnancy, literacy,
وتشمل تلك القياسات متوسط العمر و التعليم و الحمل في سن المراهقة
social mobility, just to name a few.
والحركية الاجتماعية وأشياء أخرى.
Now, those of you in the audience who are Americans may wonder,
ربما البعض من الأمريكيين في الجمهور هنا يتساءل
well, where does the United States rank?
ما وضع الولايات المتحدة من حيث الترتيب؟
Where does it lie on that chart?
أين تقع على المخطط هذا؟
And guess what?
واحزروا ماذا
We're literally off the chart.
نحن خارج هذا المخطط كلياً.
Yes, that's us,
نعم هو كذلك
with the greatest income inequality
لدينا أعلى نسبة عدم تساوي في الدخل
and the greatest social problems, according to those metrics.
ومشاكل اجتماعية هي الأعلى بحسب هذه القياسات.
Now, here's a macro forecast that's easy to make,
هذه بعض التنبؤات العامة للأسواق وهي سهلة الأعداد.
and that's, that gap between the wealthiest and the poorest,
هذه هي الفجوة بين الأغنياء والفقراء.
it will get closed.
سوف تنعدم
History always does it.
هذا ما يفعله التاريخ دائماً.
It typically happens in one of three ways:
ويحدث ذلك بإحدى الطرق الثلاث التالية:
either through revolution, higher taxes, or wars.
أما بالثورات أو الضرائب المرتفعة أو الحروب.
None of those are on my bucket list.
ولا أتمنى أن يحدث ذلك في حياتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, there's another way to do it,
يوجد حل آخر لهذا ،
and that's by increasing justness in corporate behavior,
وذلك عن طريق زيادة العدالة في سلوك الشركات
but the way that we're operating right now,
ولكن بحسب ما نقوم به الآن
that would require a tremendous change in behavior,
فإننا بحاجة إلى تغيير هائل في سلوك الشركات
and like an addict trying to kick a habit,
تماماً كشخص مدمن يحاول التخلص من إدمانه.
the first step is to acknowledge that you have a problem.
وعلينا أولاً الاعتراف بالمشكلة
And let me just say, this profits mania that we're on
ودعوني أقول لكم بأن جنون الربح لدينا
is so deeply entrenched
متعمق بشكل كبير
that we don't even realize how we're harming society.
بحيث أننا لاندرك كيف أننا نقوم بأذية المجتمع.
Here's a small but startling example of exactly how we're doing that:
سأعطيكم مثال بسيط ولكنه مذهل على طريقة عملنا هذه،
this chart shows corporate giving
يمثل المخطط التالي مقدار مساهمة الشركات،
as a percentage of profits, not revenues, over the last 30 years.
كنسبة من الأرباح وليس العوائد على مدى الثلاثين سنة الأخيرة
Juxtapose that to the earlier chart of corporate profit margins,
لنقارن ذلك مع المخطط السابق لهامش أرباح شركة ما
and I ask you, does that feel right?
ودعوني أسألكم، هل ذلك يبدو منطقياً؟
In all fairness, when I started writing this, I thought,
بكل شفافية، عندما كنت أكتب عن هذا بدأت أفكر
"Oh wow, what does my company, what does Tudor do?"
ماذا تعمل شركتي (تودور)؟
And I realized we give one percent of corporate profits
وأدركت بأننا نقوم بالتبرع بواحد بالمئة فقط من أرباح الشركة
to charity every year.
إلى الجهات الخيرية كل عام
And I'm supposed to be a philanthropist.
ومن المفترض أن أكون محبا للخير.
When I realized that, I literally wanted to throw up.
عندما علمت بهذا الأمر كدت أن أتقيأ.
But the point is, this mania is so deeply entrenched
المشكلة أن هذا الهوس متجذر لدينا،
that well-intentioned people like myself don't even realize that we're part of it.
وأن هناك أصحاب نية طيبة مثلي لا يدركون أنهم جزء من هذه المنظومة
Now, we're not going to change corporate behavior
ولكن لا يمكن تغيير ذلك
by simply increasing corporate philanthropy or charitable contributions.
ببساطة عن طريق زيادة المساهمة في العمل الإنساني والخيري للشركات
And oh, by the way, we've since quadrupled that,
وبالمناسبة لقد قمنا بمضاعفة ذلك أربع مرات في شركتنا
but -- (Applause) -- Please.
ولكن... (تصفيق)... أرجوكم
But we can do it by driving more just behavior.
يمكننا القيام بهذا من خلال تصرف وسلوك عادل للشركات
And one way to do it is actually trusting
ويمكن فعل ذلك من خلال الثقة الحقيقية
the system that got us here in the first place,
بالنظام الذي أوصلنا إلى هنا في المقام الأول
and that's the free market system.
وهو نظام السوق الحر
About a year ago, some friends of mine and I
قبل سنة تقريباً بدأت أنا وأصدقائي
started a not-for-profit called Just Capital.
عملا غير ربحي يدعي ( جست كابيتال)
Its mission is very simple:
رسالتنا بسيطة جداً
to help companies and corporations
هي مساعدة الشركات
learn how to operate in a more just fashion by using the public's input
لتتعلم كيف تعمل بطريقة عادلة باستخدام مدخلات من قبل العامة
to define exactly what the criteria are for just corporate behavior.
لتحدد بدقة المعايير اللازمة لسلوك عادل للشركة.
Now, right now, there's no widely accepted standard
حتى الآن لا يوجد معايير متفق عليها على نطاق واسع
that a company or corporation can follow, and that's where Just Capital comes in,
يمكن لشركة اتبعاها وهنا يأتي دور (جست كابيتال)
because beginning this year and every year we'll be conducting a nationwide survey
لأنه في بداية هذا العام وكل عام سنجري استطلاعا على مستوى البلد
of a representative sample of 20,000 Americans
على عينة من عشرين ألف أمريكي
to find out exactly what they think
لنتعرف على آرائهم تحديداً
are the criteria for justness in corporate behavior.
حول معايير السلوك في الشركة العادلة.
Now, this is a model that's going to start in the United States
وهذا نموذج سوف نبدأ به في الولايات المتحدة
but can be expanded anywhere around the globe,
ولكن يمكن تعميمه على مستوى العالم.
and maybe we'll find out
وربما سنكتشف
that the most important thing for the public
أن أهم شيء للناس
is that we create living wage jobs, or make healthy products,
هو خلق فرص عمل كريمة أو إنتاج منتجات صحية
or help, not harm, the environment.
أو نقوم بمساعدة البيئة وعدم الضرر بها.
At Just Capital, we don't know, and it's not for us to decide.
في شركة (جست كابيتال) ليست مهمتنا أن نقرر
We're but messengers,
ولكن نحن نقوم بدور الساعي
but we have 100 percent confidence and faith in the American public
ولدينا ثقة وإيمان مئة في المئة في الشعب الأمريكي
to get it right.
في أن يحقق ذلك.
So we'll release the findings this September for the first time,
سنقوم بإظهار النتائج في سبتمبر للمرة الأولى
and then next year, we'll poll again,
وسنقوم السنة القادمة بالاستطلاع مرة أخرى.
and we'll take the additive step this time
وسنقوم بخطوة إضافية هذه المرة
of ranking the 1,000 largest U.S. companies
بتصنيف أكبر ألف شركة أمريكية
from number one to number 1,000 and everything in between.
من واحد إلى ألف وما بينهما
We're calling it the Just Index,
وسنسميه مؤشر (جست إندكس)
and remember, we're an independent not-for-profit with no bias,
واعلموا أننا مستقلين وغير ربحيين وغير منحازين لأي طرف
and we will be giving the American public a voice.
ولكننا سنعطي صوتًا للشعب الأمريكي
And maybe over time, we'll find out that as people come to know
وربما سنجد مع مرور الوقت أن الناس بدأوا يعرفون
which companies are the most just,
الشركات التي فيها عدالة أكبر.
human and economic resources will be driven towards them,
وستتوجه إليها المصادر الاقتصادية والموارد البشرية.
and they'll become the most prosperous
وسيصبحون الأكثر ازدهاراً
and help our country be the most prosperous.
وسيساعدون بلدنا على الازدهار.
Now, capitalism has been responsible for every major innovation
الرأسمالية كانت وراء كل ابتكار
that's made this world a more inspiring and wonderful place to live in.
وهذا جعل العالم مكانًا ملهمًا ورائعا ً للعيش.
Capitalism has to be based on justice.
ويجب أن تقوم الرأسمالية على العدالة.
It has to be, and now more than ever,
الآن أكثر من أي وقت مضى
with economic divisions growing wider every day.
ومع اتساع التشعبات الاقتصادية يوما بعد يوم
It's estimated that 47 percent of American workers
فإنه يقدر بأن 47 بالمئة من العاملين الأمريكيين
can be displaced in the next 20 years.
يمكن أن يصرفوا من العمل في العشرين سنة القادمة.
I'm not against progress.
أنا لست ضد التقدم،
I want the driverless car and the jet pack just like everyone else.
اريد الحصول على سيارة تعمل بدون سائق والسترة النفاثة مثل أي شخص آخر.
But I'm pleading for recognition that with increased wealth and profits
ولكني اريد الإقرار أن الثروة والأرباح المتزايدة للشركات
has to come greater corporate social responsibility.
تستوجب مسؤولية اجتماعية كبيرة.
"If justice is removed," said Adam Smith, the father of capitalism,
يقول (آدم سميث) الأب الروحي للرأسمالية
"the great, the immense fabric of human society must in a moment
" إذا ألغيت العدالة فإن النسيج الإنساني الاجتماعي
crumble into atoms."
سيتفتت وينهار".
Now, when I was young, and there was a problem,
عندما كنت شاباً وكان هناك مشكلة ما
my mama used to always sigh and shake her head and say,
كانت والدتي تتنهد و تومئ برأسها وتقول
"Have mercy, have mercy."
"عليك بالرحمة والرأفة"
Now's not the time for us, for the rest of us to show them mercy.
أنه ليس الوقت المناسب لنا لنري الآخرين الرأفة والرحمة.
The time is now for us to show them fairness,
الوقت مناسب الآن لنريهم العدل
and we can do that, you and I,
وباستطاعتنا فعل ذلك، أنا وأنتم
by starting where we work, in the businesses that we operate in.
من خلال مكان العمل الذي نعمل به
And when we put justness on par with profits,
وعندما نكون عادلين بشكل متوازن مع الأرباح
we'll get the most wonderful thing in all the world.
سنحصل على أجمل شيء في العالم
We'll take back our humanity.
سنقوم باسترداد إنسانيتنا
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)